Guide to the Hammond family papers, 1751-1914, bulk 1820s-1890s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Hammond family papers 1751-1914, bulk 1820s-1890s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Hammond family.
6.0 Linear Feet Approx. 3507 Items
Residents of Frederick County, Maryland.
Collection consists chiefly of business and legal papers of various members of the Hammond family of Maryland. The earliest items (1750s-1820s) are land grants and other land records of Nathan Hammond and Vachel Hammond. The papers of Thomas Hammond, who served as a judge of the Orphans' Court of Frederick Co., are mainly the records of his service as administrator of several estates or as guardian of orphans, but also include farm records, financial receipts, and slave purchases. The papers of Dawson V. Hammond, brother of Thomas, concern the administration of estates, including Thomas's holdings. There are a few references to Unionist sympathies in Maryland during the Civil War and economic conditions in the U.S. during the 1870s.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Hammond Family papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1947 to 1957.
Collection Overview
Collection consists chiefly of business and legal papers of various members of the Hammond family of Maryland. The earliest items (1750s-1820s) are land grants and other land records of Nathan Hammond and Vachel Hammond. The papers of Thomas Hammond, who served as a judge of the Orphans' Court of Frederick Co., are mainly the records of his service as administrator of several estates or as guardian of orphans, but also include farm records, financial receipts, and slave purchases. The papers of Dawson V. Hammond, brother of Thomas, concern the administration of estates, including Thomas's holdings. There are a few references to Unionist sympathies in Maryland during the Civil War and economic conditions in the U.S. during the 1870s. A later addition to the collection in the last two boxes consists of legal papers and financial volumes.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Hammond family
Hammond, Dawson V.
Hammond, Nathan
Hammond, Thomas
Hammond, Vachel
Agriculture -- Maryland
Executors and administrators -- Maryland -- Frederick County
Land grants -- Maryland -- Frederick County
Orphans -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Maryland
Probate courts -- Maryland -- Frederick County
Slavery -- Maryland
Maryland -- Politics and government -- 1861-1865
United States -- Economic conditions
Contents of Collection
- Hammond Family papers, 1751-1914, (8 boxes)
  - 1751-1824 (Box 1)
  - 1825-1833 (Box 2)
  - 1834-1845 (Box 3)
  - 1846-1851 (Box 4)
  - 1852-1863 (Box 5)
  - 1864-1875 (Box 6)
  - 1876-1914 and undated (Box 7)
  - Financial and legal papers, 1800s-1890s (Box 8)
    Some materials require careful handling due to brittleness.
  - Financial ledger, 1840s-1890s (Box 8)
  - Financial journal, 1810s-1870s (Box 9)
  - Financial ledger, 1840s-1880s (Box 9)